A college in Tokyo?
東京的大學？
That's fine and all, but why do you want to go there?
好是好，但你為什麼要去東京？
A production company?
製作公司？
Is that really the kind of work you want to do?
你真的想做這種工作嗎？
Find your dream, Akira. Biggest one you can.
輝，你要有自己的夢想，越大越好
A man without a dream is nothing more than a jellyfish.
男人沒有夢想，就跟水母沒有兩樣
Like you know anything.
說得好像你很懂一樣
You're just…
但你只不過是…
a country farmer.
一介農夫而已
Man! We're almost at Akira's hometown!
太好了，我們總算快到輝的家鄉了
I sure hope your parents are all right.
希望你爸媽都沒事
They'll be fine!
他們不會有事的
My parents wouldn't go down that easily!
我爸媽可沒那麼容易倒下
As your best friend, I have to introduce myself to them!
身為你最好的朋友 我一定要讓他們認識我
I'll entertain them with a one-liner!
就用我的笑話來娛樂他們吧
I'll draw them in by getting naked.
我會全身脫光光引起他們注意
It's been three years since you visited your parents, right?
你已經三年 沒回鄉探望父母了，對吧？
You're not nervous, are you?
你不會緊張吧？
No! Not at all!
不會，一點都不緊張
Well, honestly, it's gonna be kind of awkward.
老實說，到時一定會很尷尬
Now that I've quit my job, I don't know what I'm gonna say when I see him.
如今辭去了工作 真不知道見到他時該說什麼
Akira!
輝！
What's going on?
這是怎麼回事？
I'll go check it out!
我去看看
Zombies.
是殭屍
Your village is past this tunnel, right?
你家的村莊就在隧道另一頭，對吧？
-You don't think… -The villagers have…?
-該不會… -難道村民都…
No. I don't recognize anyone in there.
不，那些人我一個都認不得
Anyway, since we can't get through the tunnel,
總之，既然無法通過隧道
there's only one other way to continue.
只剩下一個方法能前進了
We'll cut through the forest, and go over the mountain.
我們要穿越森林，翻過山頭
Don't worry.
別擔心
The entrance and exit of the tunnel were sealed.
隧道出入口都封死了
They probably managed to seal out the zombies who came from the cities.
他們可能成功擋住了城市過來的殭屍
I'm sure the villagers are safe.
我相信村民一定沒事的
-A scream? -Where is it coming from?
-有人尖叫？ -從哪裡傳來的？
Out of the way!
閃開！
A zombie boar?
殭屍野豬？
Please get down!
快趴下
Oshite mairu!
我來也！
Are you all right?
你沒事吧？
Man, you really did me a solid back there!
你們剛剛真的幫了我一個大忙
My name is Masaru Kumano! Nice to meet you!
我叫熊野勝，很高興認識你們
Mr. Kumano, what are you doing so deep in the forest?
熊野先生，你跑到森林深處做什麼？
What am I doing? The cities are overrun with monsters, aren't they?
做什麼？ 城市都被怪物佔據了，不是嗎？
I was looking for a safe place and ended up settling here!
我想找個安全的地方 最後就落腳在這了
That monster boar was unexpected, though!
沒想到卻遇上殭屍野豬
Home is where you make it! I understand!
人在哪裡家就在哪裡，我明白
But you can't live in the middle of the forest!
可是這種森林深處怎麼住人呢？
This is…
這是…
Could it be?
這該不會是…
It's a treehouse, of course!
當然是樹屋囉
Despite how things seem, I'm a master carpenter!
別看我這樣， 我可是木工的工頭呢
No house? No problem, I can just build one!
沒有房子？沒問題，我自己蓋一棟
Based on how things have been going…
照這樣看來…
23. BUILD A TREEHOUSE
（23：蓋樹屋）
Japanischer Tischler!
他是日本木匠呢
This is an oak tree!
這是橡樹
Oaks have large, thick branches so they make perfect host trees.
橡樹的枝幹又長又粗，很適合搭樹屋
Southern trees rot too easily!
南方的樹種很容易腐爛
But you can find some northern trees in this area!
不過在這裡可以找到一些北方的樹種
This is an amazing and rare forest
這座森林又棒又珍貴
that's quite unusual from a global perspective!
真是世界級的好地方呢
Mr. Kumano, another zombie boar might attack before it's completed.
熊野先生，你完工前 可能還會有殭屍野豬來襲
This is a race against time. It'd be better if you had help, right?
時間緊迫，還是有人幫忙比較好吧？
Well, sure…
這是當然
Aren't we racing against time to see if your parents are safe?
我們不是要趕著去看 你爸媽是否平安嗎？
I can't believe you'd ignore someone in danger!
真不敢相信妳竟然會 無視面前有人身陷險境
Have some heart, Shizuka!
別這麼無情啊，閑
Your own secret base where you can stretch your wings and leave the world down below!
有個自己專屬的秘密基地 可以任意遨翔，不理會底下的世界
A building at one with nature,
和自然融為一體的房屋
where you can embrace the power of the trees!
可以擁抱樹木的力量
No limit to what you can design!
也能天馬行空地設計
A treasure trove of imagination and playfulness!
簡直是想像力與玩心的寶庫
A dreamhouse suspended in mid-air!
懸掛在空中的夢想小屋
A treehouse!
樹屋
Can we?! We only live once. Can we build a treehouse with our hands?
可以嗎？人生只有一回 我們可以為自己親手打造樹屋嗎？
I think that's a great idea.
我覺得可以
I don't understand what's going on, but I'll be counting on you!
我不知道是怎麼回事 但是就靠你們了
ENTRUST - AFFECTION - REVEAL
情，感情、同情
Honestly, why are men always so…
真是的，男生每次都這樣…
I did it!
完成了
A hose?
水管？
It's difficult to judge how level things are between trees by eyeballing it.
很難用眼睛目測樹上的平坦程度
You measure it by checking the level of a hose filled with water!
所以就用水管裡的水位來檢查
Amazing!
好厲害
I see. You're right!
你說得沒錯
Eyeballing it, I thought it was level, but I was completely off!
我用目測以為是平的，結果完全不是
If you place your nails and bolts in the right locations,
釘子和螺栓只要鑽對位置
you won't damage the tree.
就不會傷到樹
-I see!
-知道了
It's best to leave a five cm gap between boards,
木板之間最好留下五公分的間隙
so fallen leaves won't get stuck in them!
這樣落葉就不會卡在中間
-I see!
-知道了
Treehouses are built differently from tree to tree.
每棵樹的樹屋建造方式都不一樣
The tree itself will tell you how to build it,
樹本身會告訴你該怎麼做
and what kind of house it'll be.
該建造出什麼樣的房屋
If you're not sure of something, ask the forest.
如果不確定，就去問森林
The forest?
森林？
That's right!
沒錯
The foundation of a treehouse is the tree itself.
樹屋的基礎就是樹木本身
If the host tree dies, the house is done for.
如果樹死了，樹屋也完了
When you think of a tree, think about the other trees and the earth around it.
想著一棵樹的時候 也要想想它周邊的樹木和土地
By doing that, you'll become mindful of the entire forest.
如此一來，你就會注意到整座森林
And that's how you'll hear the voice of the forest.
這樣就能聽見森林的聲音
I feel like I just learned something really profound.
我好像學到了某種深奧的學問
When you think of a tree, think about the other trees and the earth around it.
想著一棵樹的時候 要想想它周邊的樹木和土地
By doing that, you'll become mindful of the entire forest.
如此一來，你就會注意到整座森林
And that's how you'll hear the voice of the forest?
這樣就能聽見森林的聲音是吧
Does that mean…
這是不是表示…
if you think of yourself and others around you,
只要想想自己和周遭的人
you'll become mindful of the whole world?
就會注意到整個世界了？
So, when the day comes when I can hear the voice of the world…
所以等到我可以聽見世界的聲音時
What will I write in my bucket list then?
我會在願望清單上寫下什麼呢？
You know, you've got quite a knack for this!
你學得挺快的
What? Really? Thank you very much!
真的嗎？謝謝你
I've always dreamed of having a treehouse since I was little.
我從小就夢想要有樹屋
That's great to hear!
真高興聽你這麼說
Come to think of it,
現在想想
my son used to pester me to build a treehouse for him when he was a kid.
我兒子小時候 也老纏著我替他蓋樹屋呢
I see!
原來啊
Where is your son right now?
那你兒子現在在做什麼呢？
Mr. Kumano?
熊野先生？
My son was bitten by my wife right before my eyes.
我兒子在我眼前被我妻子咬了
So, I had to deal with them with my own hands.
所以我必須親手解決他們
I thought I could take my time
我以為等我兒子長大
and build a tree house with my son when he was bigger and I had retired.
我也退休之後，就能和他慢慢蓋樹屋
People say when you're ready to repay your parent, it's already too late.
人們說子欲養而親不待
Turns out, it works the other way around too.
結果沒想到卻是反過來
Sorry.
抱歉
You have my support. Let's finish this together.
我來支援你，我們一起完成吧
Thank you.
謝謝
All right! Just a little more until it's complete!
好，再拼一下就完成了
Let's give it our all!
我們火力全開吧！
The treehouse is complete!
樹屋完成了！
This is the best house ever!
這是最棒的樹屋
This canned food is very delicious!
這些罐頭食物真好吃
It was the right call to grab these from the store!
從店裡拿這些真是拿對了
23. BUILD A TREEHOUSE
（23：蓋樹屋）
Mr. Kumano, it's been great working with you.
熊野先生，很高興和你合作
I'll be in the forest.
我會一直待在森林裡
If there's trouble, give me a holler, and I'll give you a hand.
如果遇上麻煩儘管找我幫忙
Okay!
好
How unusual.
真難得
I thought you would say, "I got to spend the night in a treehouse."
我以為你會說 “我可以在樹屋裡過夜了”
Yeah, well…
這個嘛…
I kinda got a strong urge to see my mom and dad.
因為我突然很想回去見爸媽
That was close!
真是好險
Aren't there any other routes we can take, Akira?
輝，真的沒有其他路可以走了嗎？
This place used to be called the "Hungry Gorge"
這裡以前被稱做“食人谷”
because of how many people died here.
因為很多人在這裡遇難
Until they opened the tunnel, this was the route to and from the village!
據說在隧道開通前 這裡就是進出村莊唯一的路
They also say my village started out as a penal colony.
據說我的村莊以前是流放罪犯的地方
Enclosed by steep mountains and valleys, it's like a remote island on land!
周圍都是陡峭的山地和溪谷 這裡根本就是陸上孤島
Hey!
嘿
We somehow managed to cross it.
我們成功穿越了
You sure grew up in a pretty wild place.
你成長的地方還真是狂野
Would you believe I was a wild child myself?
別看我這樣，我可是個野孩子呢
Yeah, I believe it.
我相信
But thanks to all this…
但是好在如此
It's very likely that everyone in the village is still safe!
村莊裡的人可能都還安好
We're here.
到了
That's my home, where I was born and raised!
那就是我出生長大的地方
Have I given anything back to my parents since becoming an adult?
我成年後有沒有回報過父母什麼呢？
Their birthdays and my first paycheck…
他們的生日 或是我領第一筆薪水的日子…
I had plenty of opportunities,
我明明有過很多機會
but I never really thought about it until now.
但是我從來沒有這個念頭，直到現在
Dad… Mom…
爸、媽…
I'll be home soon!
我馬上就到家了
No way.
不會吧
Where's everyone from the village?!
村子裡的大家呢？
Dad. Mom!
爸、媽！
Akira!
輝
This can't be happening. This can't be happening, right?!
不可能，絕對不可能吧
Please! I'm begging you! Please be safe!
拜託，求求你們一定要平安無事
Dad! Mom!
爸、媽！
Drink! Dance!
喝啦，跳啦！
What's this?
怎麼了？
Aren't you Akira, Tendo's kid?
你不是天道家的兒子，輝嗎？
Teruo! Akiko! Akira has come back!
照夫、明子，輝回來了
What?
什麼？
Akira? Akira, is that you?
輝？真的是你嗎？
Dad…
爸…
Dad! Thanks for working hard everyday, non-stop,
爸，謝謝你每天不眠不休地工作
to put me through college!
讓我唸完大學
Mom! Thanks for packing me lunch everyday and washing my rugby club uniforms!
媽，謝謝妳每天幫我準備便當 還幫我洗橄欖球隊的隊服
I wouldn't be alive today if it weren't for the both of you!
我能活到今天都是因為你們
I've just given you nothing but troubles and worries.
但我卻只會讓你們辛苦操煩
And…
還有…
I've never done anything for you!
我從來沒好好孝順你們
I used work as an excuse to not visit you for the past three years.
過去這三年都用工作忙碌 當作藉口，沒有回來探望你們
I'm sorry! I'm really sorry--
對不起，真的對不…
That hurts! What was that for?
好痛，為什麼要打我？
You return just to spill that nonsense?
你回來就為了說這些無聊話？
The world's a mess. Think a little before you act.
全世界正陷入一片混亂 你做事前要懂得先三思
Nonsense?
無聊話？
Are you all Akira's friends?
你們都是輝的朋友嗎？
You must've had a tough time crossing that dangerous path.
走過那條危險的道路一定很驚險吧
We've got plenty of empty rooms, so get some rest for now.
我們有很多空房，請好好休息吧
-Yes, sir! Thank you! -Thank you very much!
-謝謝 -非常感謝
I leave the rest to you, dear.
其他就交給妳了，親愛的
I'm off to the fields.
我要去下田了
Your dad's not the man I'd pictured.
你爸跟我想像中不一樣
-All right, we should get to work too! -All right!
-好，我們也該去工作了 -對
We forage wild plants in the mountains and vegetables from our fields.
這些是山裡採的野菜和田裡種的菜
We're a small village with nothing fancy, but please make yourself at home.
這裡是小地方，沒什麼特別的 就請當自己家吧
Thank you very much, ma'am!
非常謝謝阿姨
Thanks for the food!
開動了
Wow! This is so good!
好好吃
So this is tempura?
這就是天婦羅嗎？
Have you been locked down here sustaining yourselves
你們這段時間都關在村莊裡
all this time in the village?
在這裡自給自足嗎？
Yes, we're a remote village
對，反正這裡地處偏僻
that's pretty much sealed off every winter, anyway, with all the snow.
每年冬天遇到大雪就無法出入了
We've always survived the winter by farming and hunting.
我們總是靠農耕和狩獵度過冬天
So, this spot of trouble isn't trouble at all.
所以這點小事根本不成問題
I see.
原來如此
If I may ask…
冒昧請問
The zombies in the tunnel…
隧道裡的那些殭屍…
A lot of people from the city tried to take shelter here
很多城市人想到這裡來避難
when they heard rumors that this village was safe.
因為他們聽說這裡很安全
But some of them were infected, and they were spreading the infection.
但是其中有些人被感染 而且開始擴散
We had no choice but to seal the tunnel.
我們別無選擇，只好封住隧道
That stopped the infection in its tracks.
斷絕了感染
I'm really glad you and the others are safe!
真是幸好你們大家都平安
Anyway, a number of people from the city managed to survive.
總之，也有幾個城市人順利倖存
The village has been losing residents for a bit, so there are many empty houses.
因為人口流失的關係 這個村子裡有很多空屋
We let them use those and live with us.
就讓他們在裡頭住下來一起生活
Wunderbar!
好棒
Akira!
輝
We should add historic home renovations on your list!
要不要在你的清單上 新增翻修古民宅這一項？
That's a good one!
好主意
Hold on now!
等等
There was a reason why I came back to my parents' place!
別忘了我回來爸媽家是為了什麼
I haven't repaid Mom and Dad!
我還沒好好回報他們
I have to be a good son!
我一定要當個孝順的好兒子
31. GO HOME AND SPEND TIME WITH MY PARENTS
（31：回家陪伴父母）
This is truly a glimpse of old Japan.
這根本就是舊時代的日本
I wasn't even born here, but I feel like I've returned to my hometown.
雖然不是在這裡出生的 但卻有回到家鄉的感覺
What's this feeling of nostalgia?
怎麼會有這種懷念的感覺呢？
-Right?
-是啊
You don't need to do that!
不用麻煩啦
I'll wash the dishes for you. You can just sit back.
我來幫妳洗碗，妳去坐吧
Really?
是嗎？
Anyway, look, I got you a souvenir! It's Biyoko Tweats, a Tokyo specialty!
對了，我給妳帶了伴手禮 這是東京名產小雞饅頭
Thank you.
謝謝你
Are you tired? Want me to massage your shoulders?
累了嗎？要不要幫妳按摩肩膀？
I'm all right.
我沒事
Then how about I take you on a trip? How about a hot spring?
那我帶妳去玩好嗎？去泡溫泉？
I found a really amazing spring in the mountains recently.
我最近在山上發現一處很棒的溫泉呢
Akira, thanks for worrying about me.
輝，謝謝你的關心
But aren't you exhausted from your long journey?
不過你走了這麼遠的路不累嗎？
I can do the dishes myself, so get some rest.
碗我來洗就好，你去休息吧
Hey, Akira.
輝
I could use your help if you're free.
你有空的話可以來幫幫我
How have you been lately?
你最近好嗎？
Have your backaches gone away?
背還疼嗎？
No. It's the same as always.
是啊，老樣子了
Dad, you've really been doing this by yourself?
爸，這都是你自己一個人弄的嗎？
Working the fields sure is hard work!
種田很辛苦呢
It's not that bad.
也沒那麼糟啦
But now that I'm here, I can help you with anything!
既然我來了，我可以幫忙
You can count on me for--
你可以交給我…
Everyone in the village must work together to do their part.
村裡每個人都要團結一心 盡自己的一分力
Everyone knows that.
大家都知道這點
That's true.
這倒是
I'm having trouble making Mom and Dad happy.
怎麼樣都沒辦法逗爸媽開心
This is so difficult!
好難啊
How do you repay your parents?
到底要怎麼樣才能回報父母呢？
I don't expect I've got much time left.
我的時間已經不多了…
Dad!
爸
The green beans were ready to harvest. This should be enough for dinner.
四季豆可以收成了 這些應該夠晚餐吃…
Dad?
爸？
-Is something-- -No. It's nothing.
-怎麼… -沒事
I see. Those guys came from the city.
那些就是城市來的人
That guy… I've seen him before.
那個人…我好像在哪裡見過
-Are we really doing this? -Of course we are.
-真的要這麼做嗎？ -當然是真的
JOB SEARCH
（搜尋職缺）
Just 230,000 yen for contract work? And no bonus?
約聘只有23萬日圓，還沒有獎金？
Do they think I'm stupid?
他們當我是傻子嗎？
I guess working really is for losers.
看來只有廢物才會工作
Damn it!
可惡
I should've had that old lady get me more.
應該叫老太婆幫我買的
What a pain!
麻煩死了
When and why did I start falling behind those around me?
我是什麼時候開始 又是怎麼會這樣落後其他人的？
A life of being unwanted by society and by others.
被社會和所有人唾棄的人生
I wish I could go back to summer break
真希望可以回到
in grade school when I didn't have to think about anything
像小學放暑假時那樣什麼都不用想
and I could go to the pool with my friends every day and do whatever I wanted.
每天和朋友去泡泳池 想做什麼就做什麼
Help me!
救命
Stop it!
住手
What the hell is that?
那是什麼鬼？
Yes!
太好了
I'm free!
我自由了
I was unwanted by those guys and society!
這個社會和那些唾棄我的人們
And they've all… They've all been destroyed!
這下他們全都被摧毀了
From now on, it's summer break every day!
從現在起，每天都是暑假
Going to the public pool by yourself during summer break is pretty lame.
暑假期間 自己一個人去公立泳池也太廢了
Hey, you three.
你們三個
Do you wanna have some fun together?
想要一起找樂子嗎？
TRY OUT DRUGS
（嘗試吸毒）
Fire a real gun…
開真槍
Blow something up with dynamite.
引爆炸藥
Burn down the company that insulted me.
燒毀羞辱我的那間公司
I wanna force my tongue down a girl's throat!
我要和女生舌吻
Slap my bitch of a wife!
甩我那賤人老婆一巴掌
We've all been rejected by society.
我們都是被社會唾棄的人
It's our turn to have fun and do whatever we want.
現在輪到我們找樂子，為所欲為了
Our last summer break!
這是人生最後的暑假了
We're all just waiting to become zombies.
反正所有人遲早都會變成殭屍
But while we're waiting…
但是在那之前…
might as well do what we want.
不如來做些自己想做的事
It'd be a shame not to.
不然也太虧了吧
Next time: Hometown of the Dead I.
下一集：死者的家鄉-上